<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../Docs/XSL/Todo.xsl" ?> 

<topics xmlns:r="http://www.r-project.org">

<topic>
<title>Basics</title>
<items>

<item>
Sort out the inheritance issues with RFunctionImpl and RObjectImpl
and the interfaces and the implementation of the methods.
<br/>
I want the methods to be inherited from RObjectImpl.
</item>

<item>
Make the REvaluator a singleton, e.g. through a service
or make the factory smart enough to reuse the same object.
</item>

<item>
Allow JavaScript to pass an object to R and have this treated
as a JavaScript object. From this, allow dynamic calls to 
JavaScript methods be called.
See include/js/jsapi.h
<js:code>
</js:code>
</item>

<item status="partial">
Convert R  (non-scalar) vectors to JavaScript arrays.
<br/>
See RVariants.cpp in the inst/components directory.
</item>

<item>
Convert JavaScript hashes/associative/named arrays to R objects.
And the other way too.
</item>

<item>
Create NS exceptions in R/C++ code.
</item>

<item>
Classes for different JavaScript types.
<br/>
Should be able to use dynamic invocation via xptcall.
Can R handle this.
</item>

<item>
Call JavaScript methods from references to JavaScript objects in R.
<br/>
https://developer.mozilla.org/en/XPConnect_wrappers
</item>

<item>
Allow passing a JavaScript function to R.
</item>

<item>
Figure out XPTCall.
</item>

<item>
Make S4 objects accessible in JavaScript with 
slots accessible as obj.slot.
</item>

<item>
Allow R programmers to implement an XPCOM interface.
</item>


<item>
Find out how to build xulrunner and firefox as embeddable libraries.
<br/>
Is building  xulrunner and firefox from source
the same thing. i.e. using .mozconfig, make -f client.mk and so on.
<br/>
The browser doesn't seem to have been built, or 
more specifically, if it is, how do we invoke it?
</item>

<item>
Embed xulrunner in R so we can run GUIs within R.
</item>

<item>
Embed R within Firefox as an extension/component.
</item>

<item>
Bindings for R to access XPCOM objects.
</item>

<item>
Allow specifying R functions as event handlers.
<br/>
Can we do this in JavaScript with 
something akin to R::cb_func(obj).
What about anonymous functions.
(e.g. instead of "javascript:...." we might have "r:function(a, b) {...}"
and have R interpret that code)
Or can we do something nice via XBL.
<br/>
Look at how Python does it.
</item>

<item>
reflection.cc (line 93)
Converting nsID/nsIID to a string via ToString() but only if we
use nspr.
</item>

<item>
TestXPTCInvoke.cpp works when in the mozilla-1.9.1/xpcom/reflect/xptcall/tests
tree, but not if we use xul-runner.
Code is the same. But the compilation and  linking are different.
<invisible>
<sh:output>
c++ -o TestXPTCInvoke.o -c -I../../../../dist/include/system_wrappers -include ../../../../config/gcc_hidden.h -DOSTYPE=\"Darwin9.7.0\"\
 -DOSARCH=Darwin  -I. -I. -I../../../../dist/include/xpcom -I../../../../dist/include   -I../../../../dist/include/TestXPTC -I/Users/du\
ncan/Projects/Mozilla/mozilla-1.9.1/dist/include/nspr    -I/Users/duncan/Projects/Mozilla/mozilla-1.9.1/dist/sdk/include -I/usr/X11/inc\
lude   -fPIC  -I/usr/X11/include -fno-rtti -fno-exceptions -Wall -Wpointer-arith -Woverloaded-virtual -Wsynth -Wno-ctor-dtor-privacy -W\
no-non-virtual-dtor -Wcast-align -Wno-invalid-offsetof -Wno-long-long -fno-strict-aliasing -fpascal-strings -fno-common -fshort-wchar -\
pthread -I/Developer/Headers/FlatCarbon -pipe  -DDEBUG -D_DEBUG -DDEBUG_duncan -DTRACING -g  -I/usr/X11/include -DMOZILLA_CLIENT -inclu\
de ../../../../mozilla-config.h -Wp,-MD,.deps/TestXPTCInvoke.pp TestXPTCInvoke.cpp
TestXPTCInvoke.cpp: In function 'int main()':
TestXPTCInvoke.cpp:904: warning: format '%s' expects type 'char*', but argument 2 has type 'void*'
TestXPTCInvoke.cpp: At global scope:
TestXPTCInvoke.cpp:1325: warning: 'void DoSpeedTest()' defined but not used
c++  -I/usr/X11/include -fno-rtti -fno-exceptions -Wall -Wpointer-arith -Woverloaded-virtual -Wsynth -Wno-ctor-dtor-privacy -Wno-non-vi\
rtual-dtor -Wcast-align -Wno-invalid-offsetof -Wno-long-long -fno-strict-aliasing -fpascal-strings -fno-common -fshort-wchar -pthread -\
I/Developer/Headers/FlatCarbon -pipe  -DDEBUG -D_DEBUG -DDEBUG_duncan -DTRACING -g -o TestXPTCInvoke TestXPTCInvoke.o   -framework Coco\
a  -framework ExceptionHandling       -Wl,-executable_path,/Users/duncan/Projects/Mozilla/mozilla-1.9.1/dist/bin -L../../../../dist/bin\
 -L../../../../dist/lib /Users/duncan/Projects/Mozilla/mozilla-1.9.1/dist/lib/libxpcomglue_s.a -L/Users/duncan/Projects/Mozilla/mozilla\
-1.9.1/dist/bin -lxpcom -L/Users/duncan/Projects/Mozilla/mozilla-1.9.1/dist/lib -lplds4 -lplc4 -lnspr4
</sh:output>
Note that we change the include to get the system_wrappers,
include gcc_hidden.h, probably need the OSTYPE and OSARCH,
use nspr, g++ options, -DMOZILLA_CLIENT, mozilla-config.h;
link against xpcom plds4, plc4, nspr4, pull in libxpcomglue_s.a
<br/>
</invisible>
See RFirefox/expt/xpt/Makefile for how to get this to work
agains the build in mozilla-1.9.1/dist/{bin,lib}
</item>

<item>
Implement the mapping from R to variants and back.
</item>

</items>
</topic>

<topic>
<title>IDL</title>
<items>
<item>
Support for sequence. See RObject.idl and creating the .h file.
</item>
</items>
</topic>

<topic>
<title>Ideas for Extensions</title>
<items>
<item>
Allow tabs to be collected in a tree in a panel on the
side of the browser so that we can group them more
than just tabs.
Allow dragging the entire parent node to a new window to put them in a different window,
or for a different profile.
</item>

<item>
Record the history for a particular tab and see how we jump around
and display this in a plot that lets us see where we started
and remember why we were there.
</item>
<item>
Let me see the (Google) search string that brought me to this page.
i.e. go back through the history to the top-most page and get the search string.
</item>
</items>
</topic>
</topics>
